Guide to the William Johnston Cocke Papers, 1682-1977, bulk 1900-1960 RL.00240
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
William Johnston Cocke papers
1682-1977, bulk 1900-1960
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Cocke, William Johnston, 1904-
RL.00240
6.4 Linear Feet
Rhodes scholar and lawyer of Asheville, N.C. Collection is divided into the following categories: Correspondence (1815-1969, some transcribed); Writings (1682-1965); Speeches (1896-1965); Miscellany (ca. 1908); Clippings (1792-1975); Printed materials (1865-1977); Volumes (1886-1954); Pictures, late 19th and early 20th centuries; and an Alphabetical file (1787-1977), arranged by topic. Most of the material spans the years 1900-1960. Included are personal correspondence and materials relating to Cocke's political and civic interests; family correspondence and photographs; clippings; and scrapbooks. Cocke's many correspondents include Sam Ervin, B. Everett Jordan, and Terry Sanford. Correspondence topics include the Democratic Party; life as an American law student in England; English law compared to American law; and travels in Europe. Some letters refer to Thomas Wolfe, whom Cocke knew.
2121 Items
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The William Johnston Cocke Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a part of the Flowers Collection in 1977.
Collection Overview
Collection reflects the varied interests of Cocke. It is divided into the following categories: correspondence (1815-1969, some transcribed); writings (1682-1965); speeches (1896-1965); miscellany (ca. 1908); clippings (1792-1975); printed materials (1865-1977); volumes (1886-1954); pictures, late 19th and early 20th centuries; and an alphabetical file (1787-1977), arranged by topic. The collection covers a wide variety of topics and time periods, but most of the material has dates in the span 1900-1960. Included are personal correspondence and materials relating to Cocke's political and civic interests. His many correspondents include Sam Ervin, B. Everett Jordan, and Terry Sanford. Correspondence topics include the Democratic Party; life as an American law student in England; English law compared to American law; travels in Europe; Thomas Wolfe, whom Cocke knew; publishing efforts; and a meeting with Lady Astor and the future King Edward VII. Other items include family letters; manuscripts by Cocke's mother, Nola, including My Reminiscences of the Sixties (1861-1865) about the Reconstruction era in Tenn.; clippings regarding a proposed N.C. constitution amendment requiring a literacy test for voter registrants in the 1860s; speeches by William Cocke, Sr., mayor of Asheville, N.C.; a guardian's account book later turned into a scrapbook; a large campaign scrapbook for Senate candidate Alton Asa Lennon; Cocke-Dilworth family photographs and many albumen prints of Europe. Topics in the alphabetical file include civic clubs; United World Federalists, Inc.; the attempt to establish the state of Franklin in what is now western N.C.; legal cases regarding horse stealing, a slave sale, and other topics; court reform in N.C. and the Bell Committee; and the Commission on International Cooperation under the N.C. Dept. of Conservation and Development.
Albumen prints; Scrapbooks; United States -- Politics and government -- 20th century; Photographs; North Carolina -- History; Tennessee -- History; North Carolina -- Politics and government; Asheville (N.C.) -- History; Reconstruction (U.S. history, 1865-1877) -- Tennessee; Lawyers -- North Carolina -- Correspondence; Cocke, William Johnston, 1904-; Cocke family; Democratic Party (U.S.) -- History; Cocke, William Johnston, 1904-; Ervin, Sam J. (Sam James), 1896-1985; Dilworth family; Sanford, Terry; Jordan, B. Everett (Benjamin Everett); Lennon, Alton Asa
- Correspondence Series, 1815-1969 and undated, 2 boxes
  - 1815-1928 (Box 1)
  - 1929-1969 and undated (Box 2)
- Writings Series, 1682-1965 and undated, 3 boxes
  - Clark, William Bell, 1960 (Box 3)
  - Cocke, Nola (Dilworth), undated (Box 3)
  - Cocke, Nola (Dilworth), 1930 and undated (Box 4)
  - Cocke, William Johnston, 1949-1965 and undated (Box 5)
  - Dilworth, Sarh E. J. (Broyles), 1861-1868 (Box 5)
  - Duncombe, Giles, 1682 (Box 5)
- Speeches Series, 1896-1965 and undated, 1 box
  - Speeches and other engagement files (Box 6)
- Miscellany Series, circa 1908, 1 box
  - Various papers (Box 6)
- Clippings Series, 1792-1975 and undated, 1 box
  - Clippings files (Box 7)
- Printed Material Series, 1865-1977 and undated, 1 box
  - Other printed materials (Box 8)
- Volumes Series, ca. 1886-1954, 2 boxes
  - Nola (Dilworth) Cocke, ca. 1886 (Box 8)
  - William Johnston Cocke scrapbook, 1898-1910 (Box 8)
  - Alton Asa Lennon scrapbook, 1954 (Box 15)
- Photographs Series, late 19th and early 20th centuries, 2 boxes
  - Miscellany, late 19th and early 20th centuries (Box 9)
  - People, late 19th and early 20th centuries (Box 9)
  - Belgium, England, Ireland, late 19th century (Box 9)
  - France, late 19th century (Box 9)
  - Germany, late 19th century (Box 9)
  - Italy, late 19th century (Box 10)
  - Scotland and Switzerland, late 19th century (Box 10)
- Alphabetical Files Series, 1785-1975 and undated, 4 boxes
  - Asheville and Bunconbe county, 1929-1964 and undated (Box 11)
  - Burton Grant, 1808-1967 (Box 11)
  - Chucky Jack, 1956 (Box 11)
  - Court calendar reform, 1954-1957 (Box 12)
  - Cour cases, 1933-1952 (Box 12)
  - Court reform, 1954-1961 (Box 12)
  - Democratic National Committee, 1953 (Box 13)
  - Democratic Party, local and national campaign, election miscellany, 1904-1970 (Box 13)
  - East Tennessee Historical Society, 1955-1957 (Box 13)
  - International relations, 1948-1972 (Box 13)
  - McCarthy, Joseph Raymond, 1954 (Box 13)
  - Masonic certificates, 1883-1885 (Box 13)
  - National Trust for Historic Presercation in the the United States, 1953-1956 (Box 14)
  - North Carolina and Buncombe County Bar Associations, 1909-1965 (Box 14)
  - Recreational information, 1939-1948 (Box 14)
  - St. Mary's Catholic Church, Asheville, N.C., 1961 (Box 14)
  - Sanford, Terry, 1961-1963 (Box 14)
  - Sanford campaign, 1972 (Box 14)
  - State of Franklin, 1785-1975 (Box 14)
  - Tennessee legal papers, 1787-1793 (Box 14)
  - Trauma and cancer, 1928 (Box 14)
  - United World Federalists, Inc., 1948-1958 (Box 14)
  - Webb, Edwin Yates, 1955 (Box 14)
  - Western North Caolina Historical Association, 1954-1961 (Box 14)
  - The Wilderness Trail, undated (Box 14)
  - Wills, 1895-1905 (Box 14)
  - Women's Clubs, 1899-1941 (Box 14)
  - Vance, Zebulon Baird, 1868-1943 (Box 14)
  - Young Democratic Clubs of America, 1936-1961 (Box 14)
  - Zeb Vance Debating Society, 1946-1966 (Box 14)
- Oversize Material, 1865-1890, 1 folder
  - Presidential pardon, 1865 Nov. (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Passport, 1890 (Box 14)